You're listening to the Raiders NFL
Draft Podcast.
Here are your host, Bucky Brooks and
Rhett Lewis.
Raider Nation, welcome back. The Raiders
NFL Draft Podcast is up and running once
again and coming to you following what I
would call the capstone performance in
the draft profile of presumptive number
one pick Fernando Mendoza. Coming off
the Indiana Pro Day, uh I was there in
person. I'm Red Lewis, of course, Bucky
Brooks, former Raider, former NFL scout
with us as always. And um Bucky, we were
both on the broadcast for NFL Network of
the Proday and uh it was it was quite a
scene out there. I mean, I can tell you
as a former Indiana Hooer, it was the
biggest proday in the history of Prodays
at IU. That I can tell you for sure.
What was your kind of view of what it
all kind of looked like from your
perspective?
>> So, I think there are a few things that
are interesting when it comes to proday.
People talk about pro days aren't a big
deal, but I think you can uh follow the
breadcrumbs in terms of what people are
thinking based on how they treat the
proday. So, from the Raiders side, it
was a large contingent there. You saw
John Spek, you saw Kubiaak, uh there
were 10 officials there to see and what
you want is you're trying to get a full
assessment of the people that you're
looking at. And we'll talk about
Fernande Mendoza primarily. Everyone
wants to have an opinion. You want to
weigh. You want to make sure you get
different perspectives on how everybody
felt like he performed, how he handled
the interactions with his teammates and
those things. For Fernando, this is like
the biggest job interview that they
have. Despite all the things that he's
done, all the things that he's put on
tape, the interview that he had at the
combine, there's a different pressure
that comes to being able to perform on a
pro day. And even though we can talk
about it being the equivalent to going
to the driving range and hitting a small
bucket of balls, you still want to show
the people that are the decision makers
that you have all the goods to be that.
And I think, look, he knocked it out the
park. his interactions with his
teammates, the way that he commanded and
barked out orders to his wide receivers
and the other eligible pass catchers
that were there showed leadership, but
then the connectivity that they
displayed at the end of it. The way his
people really feel connected to Fernando
to me, that's really what you're trying
to see because we can assess all the
things on tape, but what you can't get a
true assessment of is how are they going
to fit the culture and the environment
that has already been established.
>> Yeah. Yeah, look, you're not going to
draft Fernando Mendoza number one
overall based on the fact that he threw
a 65 yard absolute dime by the way deep
shot on the money to EJ Williams down
the field. It's great to see, but that's
not why he's going number one overall.
All of those types of things you see
when you watch his 16g game undefeated,
you know, run as the quarterback of the
national champion Indiana Hoosiers.
That's all out there for you. Um, you
know, the way he reacts to defenses, the
way he reacts to prep, that's all there
for you. That's not what you're gaining
here at Proday, but what you were
talking about, part of what I got a
chance to talk to John Spitech about
there in Bloomington on Wednesday was
the way he interacts, the way he runs
it, the way he commands it. Um, now
look, I think there's certain things
about accuracy that you can see there.
Obviously
>> throwing, you know, routes on air
essentially. you want to be dang near
perfect. And he was uh maybe there's one
ball that he kind of overthrew just a
touch, one that kind of lost a little
bit of fluttered a little bit in the
air, but again, those are those are so
minor. All that stuff is so minor. Like
it was from a throwing perspective, it
was excellent. But what really stood out
and you kind of touched on it was one
his command of the moment. He was
saying, uh, you know, Elijah, you're
running the inside shake or Omar Cooper,
you're running the whip. uh you know,
Riley Noakowski, the tight end, you've
got the uh you you know, you've got the
the the deep curl, like all those sort
of things, like he was in charge. He
wasn't even like looking on the on the
script, too. It was all up here in
recall. The way he supported his
teammates the whole day. He wasn't doing
any of the testing, but he was there for
them while they were uh encouraging
them, that sort of thing. And then this
whole I got a chance to kind of go
behind the scenes with him a little bit
the week before the proday and this was
a coordinated effort not only to
showcase what he felt like he wanted to
accomplish, but to let his teammates
showcase their skills in front of all 32
teams. And I I thought one of the things
he mentioned to me in our interview
afterwards was he was like, "Look, I I
hope this is, you know, this is kind of
the last time in Bloomington, but I hope
I get to play against and play with some
of these guys in the future because that
is certainly a possibility um as we go
forward with some of the other players
like Omar Cooper, Elijah Serat, Riley
Noacowsky, the running backs Kalon Black
and Roman Hembi. Um EJ Williams, another
receiver who kind of showed up in a big
way uh in that workout. But for
Fernando, this was excellent. Um, he was
he was every Now, the the other thing
that that did sta stand out, and I want
to hit you on this size, Bucky.
>> This is a 6'5 quarterback that weighed
in at 236 pounds and looked every bit of
it.
>> Thick, firm, strong lower half. You
could tell in his forearms that there's
some extra muscle that has been built
here. He was telling me it was he's up 7
lbs and down 7% body fat uh since the
national championship game. You know
who's also 6'5 and 237 pounds? Josh
Allen.
I'm not saying that Fernando is is you
know moves the way Josh Allen does but
like that frame plays man he is a
prototypical quarterback. What was your
take on that part of it? You know, I
think that's the thing you checked off
the boxes when it talks about the
prototype. And a lot of times when we
are doing what we call body typing, uh,
assessing what a player looks like when
they walk beside us or behind us, in
front of us, we are not only looking at
like the frame and the features and
those that, but are they in shape? Has
he taken the process seriously? has he
really committed to be in shape or has
he been on the banquet circuit just kind
of hanging out and meling it in because
he assumes and everyone assumes that
he's gonna be the number one and what I
would say is I'm probably more impressed
with the way that he walked in the way
that he looked the work that you could
tell that he's been doing that's struck
with me the thing that also stood out to
me is in the interview that he talked to
with you he talked about I did not want
this to be a flashy proday where we're
doing pro proday stuff I wanted to show
that we're getting ready to play and
that the
>> pro day had a I would say a
professionalism to it. It had uh a bit
of the process that he always speaks to
like hey here's where I'm at in my
journey. Here's where I'm at and this is
where I'm trying to go. So let me do
some things under center. Let me show
you that I've worked on this stuff and
I've continued to work on it in
preparation for mini camp and training
camp and the regular season and the
things that lie ahead. So to me, the
more that I'm exposed to Fernando, the
more that I like him in terms of his
approach, his process, the
professionalism, and I will say this,
the overall presidential feel that he
has as the leader in the face of a
franchise down the road.
>> Completely in command. By the way, the
pace of that workout was I I mean, it
was moving. The tempo was hot in there.
And it was warm in there, too. like and
and it was allowed to kind of go that
fast because they had nine different
guys that he was throwing to. So, you
didn't have to wait for the receivers to
kind of catch their breath. There was a
constantly another one going and they
had that script man coordinated again.
It was they they had prepared it really
well. Um and then just on the size thing
when I was with him in Irvine watching
him work out uh before he left for
Bloomington, you know, bunch of guy
people are always coming up to him,
right? He's always very gracious with
that stuff. I I thought it was kind of
cool. Some of the groundskeepers at one
of the schools where he was throwing at
came up to him, started talking Spanish
to him, and he started talking Spanish
right back, held the whole conversation,
took photos. But that those guys, the
high schoolers that came out to watch
him. All of them were remarking at how
big he was. He's like, "Whoa." They're
all like, "Whoa, you look you're way
bigger in person." Well, he he's he's
gotten bigger and he he got bigger from
the moment he got to Indiana. like he
was he he played this season bigger than
he did at Cal and then he's gotten he's
added more good weight to his frame. And
let's not forget like he moves around
pretty well now. He's got some mobility
that can win you can get you first downs
and as we saw in the national
championship can help you win games. Um
but it can get him out of a trouble
trouble a little bit. And then I think
as we learn more about, you know, the
connection with the Raiders and with
Clint Kubak, he throws really well on
the run, Bucky. And that was something
he wanted to showcase in this proday
script as well. And that's something I
think we're going to see here eventually
within this Raiders offense is and
that's kind of been a staple of that
that this style of offense is the
ability to get out there on some of
those boots and uh some of those nakeds
and make those throws.
>> Yeah, I think it's really important. And
the reason why it's important is because
so much of the system that Kubak has
employed and the offshoots of this
system that was employed by his dad Gary
Kubak and Mike Shanahan features a lot
of play action, a lot of movement
passes, a lot of misdirection with shots
taken back side. You talked about, we've
talked about the 65 yard toss that he
delivered on a dime. Some of those
things were staples of Gary Kubak's
offense back with the Houston Texans and
they've been sprinkled in Clint Kubak
system when he's been able to run an
offense. I think we'll see that. But
watching Fernando go through everything.
Shotgun, under center, the tosses that
he was making, those are things that you
can visualize him doing with the Las
Vegas Raiders. I think if you're the
Raiders brass, you have to be excited
about his process. You got to be excited
about his progress from the end of the
season to now. And then you have to be
excited about what could take place
going forward now that you're beginning
to put your ducks in the road to set
them up for long-term success. Couple of
a couple other things about the value of
a proday, right? And the ability to have
a a really, you know, kind of
unregulated
uh touch point with him, right? There's
not a lot of constraints on what you the
time that you can spend around him in
this setting where there are in some of
the other ones with the Zooms that you
do. Obviously, in the combine interview,
it's so truncated, 15, 18 minutes, that
sort of thing. They got a chance to
obviously be around him the entire day,
watch him throw. uh he had a meeting
with Clint Kubak right after the workout
that he was going with. Then they all
had dinner together there in Bloomington
as a contingent. Um and and so like the
value of that time to kind of just be
around and really kind of get to know
him better than maybe you have at any
time elsewhere in the process. H you
know from your experience as a scout
like how how do you kind of value that
time that you can get out of proday with
a player in a situation like this?
Oh, you value it um a ton because you
don't know the player. We've only been
exposed to the player briefly. Small
interactions. Talk about the official
form interview that you have at the
combine. Maybe your pro your your scout
has kind of met Fernando in passing when
he's visited the school and those
things, but you still haven't had an
opportunity to fully build out a
relationship. Now, the league is
different where you have some Zoom
calls, but it's still nothing like
face-toface interactions. And so for the
Raiders to be able to get that, it makes
them feel more comfortable about who the
player is. And before we talk about like
what they do on the field, it's really
the comfort in the player, who you're
coaching, who you going to bring in, who
you're going to entrust to be the
designated leader of the team. You have
to be really comfortable with the
personality and you have to develop a
level of trust in that player because no
matter what people say, not only does he
carry the weight of being the number one
overall pick if he's selected by the
Raiders, but he's QB1, the new face of
the franchise. That is significant and
you have to make sure that you can trust
him with all those responsibilities.
>> Yeah. I I just uh continue to be really
impressed with the way that he carries
himself. you know, one of the questions
I was asking him um in our conversation
after uh the workout, you know, was was
about the Raiders and about all of the
external speculation about going number
one. Um and he has obviously done his
best to to kind of block that out. But I
I also kind of pressed him on, look, you
got a lot of people you're trying to
make an impression on, many of which are
here. general manager John Spyc, head
coach Clint Kubak, offensive coordinator
Andrew Janoko, who by the way played
with Indiana quarterbacks coach Tino
Sinceri, and offensive coordinator and
wide receiver coach Mike Shanahan when
they were all together at Pit, which is
which is kind of a cool connection. So
they'll they'll really get the full
spectrum of who uh Fernando is with some
of those connections. But um you know I
was asking him obviously about those
guys and then you know most notably
about minority owner Tom Brady who it's
no secret Fernando he's kind of been
Fernando's idol uh in terms of football
guys that he looks up to and watches.
And so I was like what is what is
something about you that you want to
make sure Tom Brady in addition to this
entire Raiders evaluation staff knows
about you as a quarterback? And I I
thought the the answer he gave was
pretty powerful in that he's like,
"Look, no matter what's happening in
this process, no matter how many people
put my name next to the Raiders at
number one overall in a mock draft or
talk about me going number one overall
or as the number one quarterback in this
class, I am always going to be the same
person, the same Fernando Mendoza, which
is something that I can vouch in the
time that I have spent around him and
around his teammates. He is literally
everything to everyone, always the same
dude. Um, and he is truly authentic and
he is always focused on the task at
hand. And I think those are things that
Tom can really relate to. Tom was
incredible uh at blocking out the noise,
preparing maniacally, right? And
focusing in on what the task at hand was
each and every day, each and every rep,
each and every play, each and every
game, each and every season. And that's
really at the core of who Fernando is.
So, I think that that message will
probably get relayed back to Tom because
he was not uh in Bloomington. As far as
I could tell, I don't know if he was
there in sunglasses and a mustache or
something, but as far as I could tell,
Tom was not one of the 10 Raiders
personnel that were there, but I just I
think that's something that really will
impress Tom and will be a part of that
decision-making process.
>> Yeah. No, I think it has to be a big
part of it. And you talk about being
able to uh be the same to maintain it.
And I think it continues to speak to
what Fernando always uh talks about and
that's being processoriented because
when you're processoriented, you worry
about the task at hand. You don't worry
too far ahead. You don't worry about
what just happened. You're focused on
being the best that you can be today and
improving upon the task that you have in
front of you. So, you love that. You
love to hear that. And I do believe that
Tom will uh find comfort in knowing that
Fernando's mentality and mindset is on
the here and now. And I think the other
thing at a time where so many young
people and so many young players coming
into the league can worry about other
stuff like brands and and the the the
auxiliary stuff around the game.
>> Fernando is very committed and focused
on the game because if you focus on the
game, the other stuff will come. And I
think he is wellwired to be a QB1 in
this league for a franchise as
distinguished as the uh Las Vegas
Raiders.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Uh I want to get to a couple
more things on Fernando and then hit the
Kirk Cousins news which is fresh here as
we're recording here today and then uh
bounce out of here uh for this episode.
Um but with Fernando, a couple things
that I've learned just talking to his
teammates. Um, number one, like I asked
a bunch of them, you know, when did they
know that he was going to be the dude?
Like when did they know he was like a
guy, right? Like a football dude that
could lead them to the promised land.
Uh, Aiden Fischer told me,
Aiden Fischer's a linebacker, really
good player. He's going to get drafted,
um, in my opinion. And he was like, I
was giving Fernando so much crap. I was
talking so much, you know what, to
Fernando through the first couple of
practices of spring ball and he just
kind of took it, right? We kind of
ignore it, walk away, move on. Um, and
then by practice five, Fish said
Fernando was talking some stuff back and
carving the defense up. And at that
moment, Fish was like, "Okay, like we
got a dude." Which which kind of brings,
you know, one of the final pieces of the
Fernando evaluation to me. He is a
million-dollar smile with a make you pay
mentality. He will rip your heart out
and do it with a smile on his face.
Coach Signetti called him in addition of
one of the most uh well-prepared players
he's ever coached an absolute lion of a
competitor. That toughness really
resonates with his teammates. Um and
that's the other piece that I wanted to
convey. Uh Pat Gooan, his center,
another player is going to get drafted
this year said that it was the Iowa
game. It was the scramble on third and
15 in which he picked up almost the
entire first down, got 14 of the 15 and
then got absolutely plastered on the
sideline by an Iowa defender, bounced
right back up and ended up obviously
leading a game-winning touchdown drive
in that game. um that toughness he
showed in that game on a play like that,
on a run like that that put his body on
the line to try and get a first down,
that moment and then the culmination of
the result of that game really endeared
him to his teammates. He is such a
magnetism to them. One, because he
connects with them, but two, because of
moments like that. And then there was
the Heisman Trophy thing. Last thing
I'll say on it, um, that night those
guys have said even maybe even more so
than celebrating the national title was
like the best night of their lives was
to celebrate Fernando in New York
winning the Heisman. In fact, it is the
name of their group text thread now is
thank you Fernando. Like that's how much
his teammates, you know, love him and
appreciate the player he is. So thought
that was really cool. Uh lastly, do want
to hit on Kirk Cousins, the veteran
quarterback now coming in uh to join the
Las Vegas Raiders on a what's basically
a one-year deal. The contract details
that have been reported are a little bit
convoluted. You could call it a 5year
$170 million deal, but there's void
years. There's a two-year $80 million
option, but it's essentially a one-year
$20 million deal that's fully guaranteed
with the Atlanta Falcons playing a vast
majority of that deal. So, um, he's the
veteran quarterback, right, that comes
in that that Clint Kubak talked about.
He would rather he would like to have a
veteran quarterback to not pressure a
rookie in there. What does this do for
the Raiders, for the quarterback room,
and for the probability of Fernando
Mendoza joining as the number one pick?
>> Well, one, let's talk about the
quarterback room and how important it
is. Uh, some people always talk about
it's important that you have a
quarterback room where you have guys who
have similar skill sets. I would say
that it's really more important in this
situation that you have guys that have
similar mentalities because Kirk Cousins
has run the full gamut uh throughout his
career. He's a guy that came in as a
fourth round pick, had to uh win a
competition with RG3, become the
starter. He's made a ton of money. He's
been very successful, played at a Pro
Bowl. He's done it as QB1. To me, he is
the perfect muse for Fernando Mendoza.
And when you think about Kirk Cousins
personality and demeanor, they're more
similar than different when it comes to
how they go about doing their things,
how they approach business, business,
and that. And I am sure that there's
been a conversation about Kirk Cousins
being a willing mentor to Fernando
Mendoza and them being able to exchange
information throughout the course of
week training camp, how to prepare for
Kirk Cousins to be able to show Fernando
a process for getting ready. That is
also critical. all those things because
I've heard it so many times from
quarterbacks where Alex Smith talked
about laying the foundation for Pat
Mahomes and showing him how to prepare.
To me, it's about
>> passing it on, paying it forward, Kurt
Cousins has the ability to do that while
Fernando Mendoza is learning how to be a
pro from a guy who's been a very
established and successful pro for a
long time.
>> Yeah, maybe teaches him how to get a
fully guaranteed salary for 11 straight
years.
over and over. Again, one thing that
Kirk Cousins has done is he has made a
ton of money, he's made it in a way that
is unique. And as
>> uh Fernando Mendoza is updating his
LinkedIn page as he has aspirations of
being a terrific businessman.
>> Who who to look better to
>> what a great man than Kurt Cousins who
takes care of business in a major way.
>> Yeah, really clever. Also, the way I
mentioned the contract stuff, the way
that the Raiders were able to structure
this deal to get the maximum offset out
of the Falcons to pay the, you know, a
bunch of that salary and to have it all
work out. And I think this is a
beautiful, beautiful match in that
quarterback room. So, a lot to look
forward to if indeed Fernando is the
number one pick, but it certainly feels
like that is still the way that things
are going. All right, for Bucky Brooks,
I'm Red Lewis. Thanks so much to our
friends at Silver and Black Productions
and all of you for being a part of this
episode of the Raiders NFL Draft
Podcast. We are back with you next week
getting back to the business of
identifying more prospects that could
fit in silver and black. Until then,
we'll catch you next time.
Thank you for listening to the Raiders
NFL Draft Podcast.
Make sure to subscribe to the Raiders
Podcast Network wherever you get your
podcasts.